ERIC SAKAMOTO

 CV

Av. Eng. Eusebio Stevaux, 800 - Ap 172A São Paulo - SP - Brazil - 04696-000 +55 (11) 99372-0972 eric.sakamoto@gmail.com

SRE/DevOps

PROFILE

Senior-level IT professional with 24 years of experience working as a developer with distributed systems from 1999 to 2010 and as an infrastructure specialist since 2010. Experienced in architecting and troubleshooting complex multi-tier systems. Working with Cloud Technologies since 2018.

Linkedin: https://www.linkedin.com/in/eric-sakamoto-b23a381

Github: https://github.com/ericsakamoto

EDUCATION

Bachelor Degree in Physics – Specialization in Basic Research University of São Paulo – Institute of Physics - 1994 to 1999

EXPERIENCE

Senior Tech Engineer - SRE, C6 Bank, December 2021 - Present

C6Bank is a Brazilian digital bank startup that offers bank services to customers. Responsabilties:

- Provisioning AWS infrastructure resources such as EC2, RDS, EKS/K8S, SQS, S3, and Elasticache using Terraform
- Providing support for investment applications in development, testing, and production environments
- Participating in troubleshooting and system investigation to ensure optimal performance
- Regularly checking application health and analyzing logs to prevent potential issues
- Utilizing monitoring tools, such as Appdynamics and Grafana, for effective system tracking and problem resolution

Senior Middleware Analyst, FIS (fisglobal.com), June 2010 to December 2021

Specialized in Middleware Application Servers like JBoss EAP, WebSphere Application Server ND, WebSphere Enterprise Service Bus, WebSphere MQ, IBM Integration Bus (aka Message Broker), IBM Cloud Private (Docker/Kubernetes) and WSO2 API Manager.

Defined infrastructure architecture of applications related to credit card processing, like web portals, webservices and APIs. Responsible for supporting more than 100 applications in DEV, QA and Production environments.

FIS Middleware Infrastructure environment processes every month millions of requests of major financial companies in Brazil. Main systems:

- Prepaid Cards Alelo (payment transactions)
- Private Label Credit Cards Bradesco
- Web applications for Call Centers to provide information about FIS customers credit cards
- Webservices and APIs accessed by companies' apps (Android and iOS) to provide credit card information. Clients such as Banco Original, Panamericano, Alelo, Banco Safra, Credz, BRB, Cencosud, AFINZ, HS Financeira, NBC.

Senior System Analyst, Accenture Brazil, May 2007 to June 2010

- Project: Natura. Worked with Natura's Products Quota Management System, building new features and updating other ones. This system runs on WebLogic Application Server, using JSP, Struts, EJB and Oracle Database. Applied Scrum methodology during the project.
- Project: Itaú Bank Integrator Itaú Standard Interface. Responsible for creating and updating use cases and test cases. Managed all the errors reported by testing team and redirected them to the development team for fixing. This system was conceived to process information from different systems from Itaú Bank and generate different views (accounting and financial). It was built for Mainframe platform and was split in 2 modules: batch (Cobol and JCL) and on-line (Cobol and .Net).
- Project: Votorantim Bank Phase 2 (Software Factory). Responsible for analyzing
 Votorantim Bank system requirements and estimating the necessary number of hours for
 Accenture Software Factory to build or update programs. Created project schedules and
 allocated programmers.
- Project: Votorantim Bank Phase 1. Managed development support tools like Maven2, Trac, Subversion e Continuum. Supported developers to use these tools. Analyzed non-functional requirements in different projects.

Technical Coordinator & Java Architect, FIS (fisglobal.com), October 2005 to May 2007

Defined the architecture, technologies and design patterns applied in several Java systems used by FIS clients like Bradesco, Finasa and Mercantil do Brasil.

System Analyst, EDS Brazil, July 2005 to October 2005

Created UML diagrams to map all the functional requirements. Attended daily conference calls with EDS USA team. EDS was building a web system to integrate all the company's billings reports, using .Net and SQL Server 2000 Reporting Services.

Java System Analyst, TAM Airlines, October 2002 to July 2005

- Check-in System at Charles de Gaulle Airport in Paris. Responsible for testing and adjusting TAM airlines Check-in system at Charles de Gaule Airport, in Paris. Travelled to Paris multiple times, working together with the local staff in order to approve the system.
- Check-in System and Self-service Check-in. Refactored the Java Applet program used to check-in TAM Airlines passengers. This same Java Applet program was used in self-service check-in computers. This program shows all the seats of an airplane and informs which is free or booked.
- Airplane Catering Supplies Management System. Created a system to manage the supplies used by catering companies to prepare meals served by in-flight service. This system was built with Java (MVC, Servlets, JDBC e JavaBeans) using Oracle software (application server and database).

Programmer, Scopus Technology, June 1999 to October 2002

- Bradesco PAN CRM. Gathered functional requirements and built the system. Client/Server system created with Java to help Bradesco branch managers deal with CRM tasks.
- Bradesco Net Empresa. Developed some modules of Internet Banking for business that was created using a Scopus proprietary framework written in C language.

SKILLS

- Programming: Java, C, Python
- Technologies: Spring Boot, JEE, Javascript, Docker, Kubernetes, Git, Ansible
- Cloud: AWS EC2, S3, EKS, VPC, SQS, Elasticache, RDS Postgres, MongoDB, Terraform
- Middleware: JBoss EAP, IBM WebSphere Application Server, IBM Integration Bus (Message Broker), IBM WebSphere MQ, IBM Cloud Private, WSO2 API Manager
- Monitoring: Dynatrace, Appdynamics, Grafana
- Logging: ElasticSearch, Splunk
- Methodologies: ITIL, Scrum, DevOps
- SO: Windows, RedHat Enterprise Linux, Oracle Solaris

LANGUAGES

English: AdvancedJapanese: Basic

CERTIFICATIONS

- IELTS Academic Overall Band 7.0 (2022)
- Duolingo English Test Score 110 (2022)
- British Council EnglishScore CEFR C1 Advanced (2021)
- AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate (2017)
- AWS Certified Developer Associate (2016)
- Red Hat Certified JBoss Administrator JBoss EAP 6 (2016)
- IBM Certified Sys Admin WebSphere Application Server Network Deployment V8.0 (2012)
- Sun Certified Programmer for the Java 2 Platform (2002)